Hello, beautiful people.
This is, uh, fabric Idemy 20 25, 26, week three,
circular Fashion, uh, moderate fashion tutorial.
Um, I just dropped a couple of things in the chat.
Um, one as links
if you haven't installed a software yet.
Uh, we'll do a up, as I said yesterday.
So we start, uh, with parametric modeling
and show a couple of things in Vision 360,
and then moving into Rhino to create also another module.
So the aim that we have today is to be able
to, uh, produce a file that you can actually use
for laser cutting already.
I will do two models, uh, you can follow me as well.
So, uh, if you have an install, fusion is a very good moment
to launch the software here.
This is a free version of this version that will allow you
to have the software installed in your computer for a couple
of years, or Rhinoceros is also an alternative.
And here you can find a trial for, uh, three months.
I usually nest the pieces in, uh, in a vector
software like Scap or Illustrator.
So you can also have one of the two installed Illustrator,
I believe there is a trial for seven days,
and Inscape is of course, open source.
I also, uh, drop in the chat, uh, link of the presentation.
So in case there is time at the end,
we can also see some example of the escalations.
And I think I can, um,
share my screen and you can launch the software with me.
Okay. So this is the, uh,
what I will be demonstrating today.
Okay. Open a new file.
Uh, if it is your time opening the software,
you probably have this interface in front of you.
I'm using a Mac,
so the interface will be slightly
different if you're using Windows.
Uh, I'm not gonna hit the chat,
so please interrupt me and unmute yourself. Mm-hmm.
Sorry, I, I'm already interrupting,
but we don't see your pull, uh, fusion 360.
We only see the browser part. Oh,
Thank you.
No worries.
Okay, sorry for this one more time.
Okay, there will screen. So I think, uh, every now
it's okay.
Perfect. So, uh,
the moment you launch the software,
this is the interface that you're gonna have.
I am on a Mac, so slightly different, uh, for you may be.
If you're on Windows, um,
let me know whenever I should repeat something
or if it's not clear, because I'm not gonna read the chat.
So you can get rid of any, uh, thing that you have in front
of you and just, uh, launch a software as it is.
Um, the moment you launch it,
you might have open like a side pining that you can close
pressing on this icon with a lot of dots.
And you should be basically seeing a wide read interface
with a cube on top, right, that you're able to manipulate
with a track pad or better with a mouse.
And very important,
you have all the way at the bottom a timeline.
If you don't have it, please, um,
have a look at the settings.
They may be, um, on top, under fusion about fusion
or under your account.
It depends if you're using Windows or Mac or uh, or a Mac.
If you don't see the grid,
you can find it here in the basic settings
or in the general.
Also, be sure to, to set up in advance the
unit here.
This is the last voice.
So you, um, design units, uh,
whether you are based in the world, uh,
I usually use millimeters if you're comfortable with inches.
Also, you can go for that. I recommend you
to have a small, um, unit.
So to match also, for example,
the resolution of the laser cutter.
So these are the just, um,
few setups.
So let's say the, uh, we should be able
to see, uh, this view.
So at the very bottom, the timeline in order
to record every action, the millimeter, uh,
grid that sometimes is useful.
So, uh, to begin with, uh, fusion is, uh,
parametric software.
There is a lot you can do with the software.
You might have already had a peak earlier.
So, um, there is a design voice here that you can navigate
with the dropdown menu.
You have a lot of options for 3D modeling, for rendering,
animations and simulations, even a space for electronics.
So there is a lot you can do with just one platform.
Today, we'll focusing on 2D vector design, that means
that soft, the, the software itself also has a platform
for creating sketches.
So, uh, the very first command
and that we're gonna use is the first one icon.
The first icon here, creating a sketch.
And we will basically work in 2D.
So to enter this month is one click on the icon,
and basically we're gonna work, uh,
from 2D for the laser cutter.
So one click either on the top face,
this orange, uh, left side
or on top of the cube that you find, uh, here.
If you press the top correctly,
you should be find yourself on top, uh,
of the cube inside a sketch mode.
So then you're gonna see one icon appearing all the way at
the bottom and a big button, uh,
with a check mark in green that says finished sketch.
If that's happens, the moment you close it,
you should be able also be able to see a folder
with one sketch created with nothing inside.
So we're every time able to access back what you had.
So double click either here or all the way at the bottom.
So you just created basically an empty sketch.
I hope we are all here.
And when we are inside the sketch,
we basically have in front of our eyes
a new set of tools.
We'll basically be using only these two panels today.
So commands under create,
and a couple of things under modify.
So let's say that we want
to create a basic module.
You've seen, uh, many options yesterday from the lecture,
and I always recommend to start with something like, uh,
a polygon shape, like a circle like a square at the very
beginning to understand how we can later on connect
to models together.
So I will start, uh, with two circles, one female, one male,
and I usually begin, uh, designing the female one.
So the one that has these lines is cuts. There's lots.
And to do so, I am gonna go under create menu.
I'm gonna choose the circle.
And for all of these shapes, you basically have many, uh,
options to choose from.
Uh, there is also commands
that you can use in your, um, keyboard.
So you can type C for example,
and access the circle directly in this case, uh,
this will be linked to the center diameter circle.
So you can also, uh, click it from here.
So create circle, diameter circle one,
click on the command
and one click on the grid
You can, um, select with a pointer with your mouse,
the shape, or you can select it inside the sketch folder.
Selecting the sketch to remove the selection of, uh,
every time you can click escape in your keyboard.
We say that, uh, fusion is a parametric software, so, uh,
basically works with parameters.
Um, to do so, there is one,
a very useful command that is called, uh, there is a,
the shortcut is D in your keyboard or sketch dimension.
And this allow you to work, for example, in a scale one
to one, so to specify in advance the size of your module.
So at any point in your drawing,
you can just create any shape.
I'll do this again. Click release.
We don't put since the beginning, the, um, the dimension,
but we added a moment later.
Just clicking on the edge on the line
with this comments catch dimension, click on the edge
and you can add a value.
For example, um, I'm using millimeters, so 40 millimeters
and this is my diameter.
You're free also to move the quotation dimension wherever
you want in the space, not going to be part of the design.
So once we have, um, our circle set, we see
that now we cannot manipulate the size anymore,
so this is kind of fixed
and I usually proceed, um, whatever I do
to create kind of a grid.
So I usually make use of axis.
And to do that, I can use a line either here from one
of the first icons or down the dropdown
menu, selecting a line.
And the nice thing about fusion is that if you're over
with the mouse, with the pointer close to a line, close
to a shape, it actually, uh, gives you an idea.
For example, what is the midpoint
or if you are perpendicular vertical compared
to a line or to a vertex.
So I just want to draw an axis where the, whatever it is,
how long it is, does really matter.
So I just click from the certain point, uh, the center,
my circle, uh, all the way up.
You can see that you don't even have to hold shift
because when you see this icon,
you're basically ready perpendicular.
You can press the line, then you can press, uh, press this,
uh, check mark to confirm the line escape at any point
to, uh, escape this selection.
Uh, an interesting feature about the software is
that you can add constraints
that you can find here on top menu to, uh, add relationships
between lines, between shapes,
and you can select the kind
of line, for example, that you have.
So if you want to use this as an axis, we can just, uh,
select the line type
and say that this is actually construction line.
It's not something that I'm gonna be needed
to be part of my design.
Uh, let's say we want to make this kind of slots, the four.
So, um, there are many ways of course to do that.
The way I recommend, uh, at least infusion that you can work
with constraints, with symmetries,
with parameters is actually start to think of a shape,
um, in a modular way.
For example, I will just do half and I will mirror the rest
and I will make a pattern so that I don't have
to manually create all this slot,
but I tell the software to do it for me.
And to do that, I will just create a line, like we said
with the circle can be also anywhere
and we can move it here later,
or I will just use the axis that just create it
and we create a point on it
and a point straight somewhere else without specifying a
dimension because I'm gonna add that a moment later
through the sketch dimension.
So I can say, for example, there's going
to be five millimeters, which is going to be the half
of my line escape to skip the selection
and before actually mirroring the line
with a mirror command.
Um, well actually to specify another, uh, dimension
because lemme see what happens.
This one, uh, this line
that I just created is actually linked
to the axis that I had.
If I don't want them to be linked, I just have
to remove these zero icons that appear
with, uh, contra Z.
Command Z. You can undo
and you can redo, um,
in the same way you can have a look at the, uh, top
and click on the two others.
So I need to specify basically what is the distance between
my line and the third center point of my circle.
So in the same way, sketch dimension
and from the line to the center can specify for example, 14
or 10, and you see what happens.
So my design is basically, uh,
is getting adjusted accordingly.
It's changing every time I change the dimension.
Let's say we were good, uh, for now it's 14
and this can be five millimeters,
so it's pretty much like that.
So one centimeter long for the line.
And once I'm here, I can just basically go ahead
and in a couple of commands just recreate my module.
So I'm going to select the line, I'm going to find
the meter command also under create
Fusion is asking me, so
what is the object that I want to mirror?
Even if I didn't select in advance, I can still do it now.
So the object, the line in this case that I want to mirror,
and the mirror line, so my axis,
and this is the result.
So in the same way,
if I change the dimension to my original line,
also the second part gets updated,
I coe to go back.
And then the last thing. So if I want to create this, uh,
female model, I basically, I'm going to create a pattern.
So there is a nice option in the software to create,
for example, a circular pattern, whether you have, uh,
center points and circle.
So I'm going to find circular pattern in the dropdown menu
and select one again, the object that I want to pattern
in this case is align.
And the center point
and would appreciate very much in the software is already
the kind of review that appears.
So there are many ways to, um,
to specify the numbers in this case of repetition.
So the numbers of lines, uh, you can add the number, you can
drag the line that appears,
for example three if I'm not happy with that.
Uh, every time you, uh, create a command,
create something, fusion adds an icon.
So if you double click on the icon, you're able
to change also a moment later.
The number of lines, sub shapes or repetitions of patterns.
So this is basically the result.
So the magic part is that if I update now these numbers,
this a limit case seven, all my design basically
gets changed and
updated, right?
It was 14.
Are we all here?
I hope silence means yes.
So how to do the other one, the mail part.
So of course there are many ways you can also finish the
sketch, for example, and create a new one.
If you're happy with that.
Uh, you can export ahead your daf.
What I usually do is work in the same sketch
unless there are many shapes that can bother you.
And you can do, um,
something like copy pasting your first module.
So you can select everything
come through CV
including the module.
The moment you make a copy,
these two are actually not communicating within each other,
so they're independent.
So if they make a change to this design,
the second one will not be effect.
The, the first one will not be affected.
Uh, to make the male part.
In this case there is a, there is a trick.
So you can just use this construction that we have
and create the other lines that are complimentary
for this to work.
So in order to have a stable connection,
if you have materials, um, or thickness
or let's say, um, one millimeter, so basically, um,
or less, um, we can ignore
the width of the line.
So we can just have one line for cutting, like in this case.
And to do that here, we can basically
remove everything except the first
line that we have created.
I, We're gonna
try to recreate this other tool here.
So once again, we can take our line
until it intersect the circle.
You can also make it longer confirm
and use the, the scissors like to trim the parts
that you don't want to be part of your design.
You can get a kind
of a review in red and select the party.
Don't want to be part, uh, of the drawing of the sketch.
So this is my line.
I also can get read of
the one I drew before, you can select it
and then, um, delete in the keyboard
or again, uh, click the scissors.
And like we did earlier, you can add a dimension to it.
So for example, according to this dimension
and the line that I read earlier, my correct dimension
for this line is eight point something.
And then I'm gonna do what I did earlier.
So I'm gonna click the mirror command.
So I'm gonna find also here down the dropdown menu,
click mirror, select the object that I want
to mirror in this case, this line select the mirror line,
so the one I already drew earlier and confirm.
Now these two are basically linked
and you can see if everything is correct,
you'll see the icon.
And then basically, once again, it's the workflow.
So under create, I'm gonna create a circular pattern.
I'm gonna select both of the lines that I adjust you
and my center point.
If I'm happy with that, I don't need to change dimensions
or if I want, I can basically, um, change everything
and update the second one accordingly.
If I select the shape, I can press m in the keyboard,
I'm able to move closer.
For example, I can use the arrows.
I can specify a dimension here,
but actually, uh, drag in the square, I'm able
to move the shapes, uh, wherever I want in the canvas,
Just for the sake of the demonstration.
For example, you could nest the shapes here,
you can also align the two of them better.
The best way to align together to circle is, for example,
using the center point
because you're not really, um,
you cannot really get a point along the circumference.
So if you have an xi, you can just select the shape you want
to move, click, move,
and then specify, for
example, a point.
No. So select your pivot point
and the more you zoom in, fusion, um, shows kind of this,
uh, magnetic lines.
So there are kind of a snaps
that help your line lines together.
So when you're happy with that, this is the result.
You can just go ahead
and guess what, create, uh, rectangular patterns.
So for example, um, you like the way they are.
Well, there's actually one thing to mention, um, that,
um, the construction lines will be
still visible in the other.
So for example, you just want to, um, make loans for all
of them as they are, maybe it's recommendable
to remove this line in case you don't want to keep it
to do more operations.
So now the shapes, let's say are, are cleaner and this one.
So I select both of them.
I go ahead and create the rectangular pattern.
So this way I'm able to multiply
with just one command all my circles and rows
and columns as much as I need, as much as I want.
So you can put once again the number five
five
and see advance the preview.
So this is basically the result.
You have, uh, we have our circle.
There are as much as possible close to each other.
There are closet loops.
The way you can see this infusion is
because you can click inside different areas
and there are this kind of, uh, uh, bluish.
And unfortunately in this case, this is the, is a bit
of leftover of material that you can actually use.
No. So think of uh, creating other connections here.
Make use of the shape
or transform these into another module.
So this is a way to, um, create a shape
and also testate inside the same software.
If you're happy with that, you can just do finish sketch
red, click on the sketch and go ahead and export the d
and d xf.
Be sure that the unit matches the unit that you were using.
So in this case, millimeter
and uh, fusion, you're able to save in the cloud as well.
The file on your computer locally circles
You Find on desktop
and for example,
you're able to import it in an file, uh,
software like Illustrator or Inscape.
And every time, uh, you import this into, uh, this kind
of software, be sure
that you're still working in the original size.
So one-to-one
and sometimes to the conversion.
This, uh, this happens, I actually think that I made,
um, a copy that is hidden
the moment I was copying the columns.
So you can do this once again, you undo wherever, um,
whenever there is a mistake, and then create again your
button
Every time in order to export, you need to get out
of the sketch mode and then right click export the
itself millimeters.
Yes, three plus two.
Yeah. And here they come pretty good.
And then, like we said yesterday, in uh, in any
of these software, you're able
to change the color of the line.
So be sure they are, for example, red or any of the RG beef.
So either red green
or blue, 2 55 0 0 web colors.
And usually we put the, um, the stroke to be zero,
uh, 0.1 millimeters
with comma or hairline wherever it is available.
And when you're done, you can just save uh, the file as PDF.
Of course, in this case we said better
to use the leftover material that appears here
because these shapes are not perfectly isolated.
Uh, this is also vector files, so of course, so you are able
to change the size, you can select everything
and work, uh, at a, for example,
want them to me to be smaller
or bigger, which if
you can keep the selection active
till they also done the form.
And of course you can make groups, you can make, uh, copies,
controversy, conv, you can clone them
and also illustrator, um, liking scape as this kind of, um,
snaps that you can enable, uh, from the settings.
So they allow you not to have gaps in between the lines.
And if you're happy with that, you can just go ahead
and save a PDF for this software.
Laser cut, um,
or any other format,
any EPS is fine.
SVG is fine. And just
go ahead and save it.
Do you have any, any questions so far?
If not, uh, we'll move to Rhino.
Okay, so in Rhino,
this is another model that I wanted to do,
which is basically the one I just laser cut
and we can go again.
So I mac
the interface will be slightly different than Windows.
This is the, also the, uh, red, no zero version seven,
maybe also a little bit different than the eight
or any previous version.
Uh, what you need to know about the software.
So it is not parametric.
Does it have a timeline like fusion
that you can record the actions and go back in time, uh,
but still undo, redo this kind of commands the work.
Um, it's not pattern metric
unless you use Grasshopper,
which is the generative environment that probably,
I'm gonna have a look at the week of computational couture.
Uh, the moment you launch the software, um,
you will be asked also to select a unit,
um, unless you, you basically skip
that, uh, that option.
My advice is like fusion to work in a millimeter
or any unit that is more
so you can see also here at the very bottom millimeters.
And at any point you're able to, uh, go back to the settings
and change, um,
uh, any of this like the grid
and any other preference, even the colors, uh, of those, uh,
my recommendation is to keep active, uh, the grid.
So, uh, sometimes, uh, these axis are useful
as well as the panel that you see here on the left
that basically allows you to, uh, select the kind of snaps
that you want to, um, to use, um,
to align, for example, shapes, lines,
or manipulate
them, uh, in the design.
So I usually select end point
liter center midpoint.
According to the shape that I'm using intersection,
I try not to use near
because sometimes it can be very confusing and vertex.
Um, on top you can select auto
grid snap if you want the pieces
or the lines to be able
to align automatically at the axis at the grid.
Uh, gumball and is three are also useful to be tick.
And in like fusion
we will basically working on the top view.
So to enter this part, we can
for now forget about the 3D views, the perspective
and double click on the top.
Um, on top in the same way, you also have commands
and we'll be using the standard mode
and basically the commands that you have here on the left
Rhino is also, uh, an option, like a command line
where you can just write the name of a command
in case you don't remember the icon or,
or if that workflow is more comfortable for you.
Uh, on the other side, on the right,
there are basically layers.
That means that you can also create new ones.
You can, um, address multiple shapes, multiple patterns,
multiple 3D models at the same time,
and be able to distribute them for a better organization.
Uh, for now we can forget about that.
If you want to change the color of your lines,
you can just double click, um, on the color
that you find here and, uh, and choose any other one.
Um, let's go back to the model
and let's try to create something different than
a circle, for example.
Um, a shape like this that
has at the same time the possibility to connect
with female male.
So something a bit iterated from here like that.
We can also do the other way around.
So we start again from the female just
to understand the workflow
and we transform this into something
a little bit more advanced.
Um, there are many ways of course, also I know
to create the shape, uh,
we'll follow something similar, um, confusion.
So I can just, uh, for example write rectangle
or click the icon that I find here
below my, um, pointer.
The selection tool. Wherever you find you see this little,
uh, dropdown arrow, you're able to select,
you have multiple options for the same shape,
for the same command.
Some of the, uh, icons here are basically shapes,
arc lines, and some others reflect more commands like
bullions, the possibility to make groups to trim,
to cut objects, uh, to join lines
or to explode them, add text and so on.
So let's start simple. Let's create, um, our polygon.
We can take a rectangle,
we can also write it so rectangle.
And once again, the software is telling me,
um, documentate.
So, um, I can just click on the grid
or specify with the value, my initial point
and the second one.
So the opposite corner in Rhino,
there is no possibility to add at a later moment, um,
the dimension, you can measure any line, any shape,
but uh, you don't have this possibility like fusion.
So, uh, one good way to do it is, for example,
nine click in command.
Uh, actually I usually, uh, position the shapes to be, uh,
in the middle of the grid.
So I can just click the rectangle or my polygon
and just write, for example, zero comino,
which is the origin, origin of my grid.
So in this case, my shape will be perfectly
aligned to the axis.
And then you can write, for example,
the dimension in this case is a square.
So we can write, uh, 40
and 40 If you're not
sure what is the dimension, there are two ways you can write
distance and select one point from one point
to another on the shape.
So you can read here either at the bottom or from top.
It depends if you are on windows.
So my shape is 40 millimeters,
or you can write dimension like DIM
and you have kind of a quotation, like a dimensions
that are not part of your design
and you can delete, uh, move at any point.
This is kind of a reference.
So if your shape,
um, is designed correctly, you should be able
to see a closed loop made of for different
lines that are yellow.
The moment you select them,
let's say this, I actually don't need it, so I can
also remove it.
And let's take one step further. So let's rotate it.
So I can design, for example, my line,
um, this way.
So in order to rotate it, uh, high multiple options,
I can select my shape with select all Ctrl o Ctrl A.
I can just write, for example, rotate if I don't know
where the icon is.
And then I can specify a center of rotation.
Uh, in order to locate a center, you need to have these kind
of snaps activated.
So you can either click the center, uh, of the grid
or a center of your rectangle of the square.
For example, I can use the one of the grid,
and again, I can write either 0.10 if I want to be specific
or just click, um, with a mouse.
And then I can specify an angle of rotation.
Yeah, in this case we can keep it 45.
Then you can just confirm your selection
and magically, uh, your shape will translate 45 degrees.
We can actually, um, fill it a little bit the edges
to make them a bit more rounded, like this module.
So, uh, the reason I command the way it's called fill it,
and I think it is, uh, one of those icons here,
like this one maybe.
So fill it. And the software is asking me
for example, to specify the lines and specify, uh, radios.
For example, three millimeters, four millimeters.
Every time you want to, um, replicate the same command,
you can actually click on space bar
so you don't have to write it again
or click again on the icon.
So select the first script to fill it,
and then the second one to apply.
And then again, space bar and the two of them.
And of course you could control the point manually.
And this case is definitely easier, uh, to do
with the command and select the lines one by one.
And similarly to fusion escape every time
to escape the selection.
So we are, let's say halfway, let's design the the joints
so we can proceed in a similar way.
Uh, as before we can create, um, access, for example,
uh, in the similar way of fusion.
Uh, you can just, for example, having a midpoint selected,
go closer zone in a little bit
and find the midpoint of your shape.
And this is something that is detected automatically.
The moment you're very close to the line.
So you can just click here
and click for example to the opposite vertex.
And then we enter,
or uh, backspace, you can confirm the selection
and then we can proceed.
We can take a line or another ways, for example, is
that you specify since the beginning the distance
between the vertex and the line.
So to do that you can take a polyline
and from top you can write the dimension.
So what is the next point of my polyline, for example, uh,
10 millimeters, one centimeter, and then confirm.
And then from here we can have our line,
let's say we can also put, it
can also draw a 10 millimeters line.
So it, once again, a select poly line doesn't matter
where I design here because I can always move
it and align it.
So one centimeter, I already kind of have a preview
and then enter to confirm the selection.
We can move it in many ways
and we can also align it
to my previous selection in many ways.
So one way is, for example, to select both
of the lines I want to se, to align
and find this icon
or just write, align
and align vertically.
And then for example, I know I don't need this kind
of access anymore, so I can just remove it.
Or of course I can have the midpoint selected.
I can write move and I can move my line
or my shape from the midpoint to my line
to the edge, to the end point of my line.
And in the same way, I already get a
review before confirming.
So if I like what I do, yeah, I just go ahead.
So I drew my first second action point,
my first slot, and I can also, the bag
that I write dimension.
So from one end to another one, I know that this is 10,
I can also add them here or remove them.
They will not impact any way in my design at all.
And let's do a pattern.
So one way, for example, you could mirror this
and then mirror it again, you can copy paste by hand.
But since uh, the software allows you to do that,
you can already for example, write, uh, in rhino,
it is called differently.
And you can find the command under this icon.
So in case we have a center
or a circle, we can use the polar array.
So we can click on the icon, click on the command
and specify the center.
If we're not able to locate it for some reason,
we can create a circle
or once again the axis that we can later on remove
and then or array,
select my object to pattern, then confirm
and the center and the number of items
to clone this case.
Yeah, we can do four. So, okay, and the angle.
So we want them to be all around.
So 360 degrees, yes.
And confirm.
So my first shape, uh, is done.
I can also make a group if I want, I can write group.
So now the moment I select the shape, um,
at turning point that are grouped,
this one and this icon is ungroup.
And we can do the next one.
So we can do, um, the mail part
or one that has a combination of both.
So we can, for example, copy paste like we did earlier,
control a select all
or just um, select with the mouse.
So copy paste in moment you copy and paste.
Uh, rhino will paste the selection exactly
on top of your shape
anyway.
We can also, uh, work on this one actually, uh, to do that.
So we go ahead in the similar way that we did earlier.
So we can use a poly polyline, we can extend our lines.
And the moment we have the intersection
as nab selected, we are able to extend the line
until it meets, uh, the line, the edge of my polygon.
So we can click here, we can confirm
which space bar, we can repeat the previous command.
And once again, from end to the intersection point,
we can remove this one
because we no longer need it.
And then we can, for example, make a pattern once again
with the center or uh, we can do something else.
For example, here we can select these two lines
to add the most to the bottom.
And we can create a mirror.
And again, For example,
what is, uh, in this case, I have to select to specify first
what is the mirror line, like a plane.
And I can just use, um, the snaps, for example,
create here since I have a midpoint.
So I can create a midpoint selecting
from one location to another
and basically have a clone of the upper part.
I can make a group control G, common G or the icon here.
And I basically made my shape.
And for example, if I want, I can just,
uh, distillate it here.
It is a perfect square, so uh,
there won't be any waste at all.
And there is a little bit of feel,
so I'm gonna lose just a tiny bit of material.
I can also use the gum to rotate, to manipulate
or to scale my shape.
I usually prefer to do it correctly, uh,
with the value spec, find math
or a number in this case might be easier
to rotate it back actually,
because we are using any way, uh, materials that are sheets.
So there are already rectangular or squared.
So we can once again go back and do, rotate
and specify the central rotation.
I can use, once again, my grid from M zero from zero
and specify, um, my degree.
For example, I can also go minus four, five
and my shape is black.
And then I can just do what I did earlier.
So I can make a pattern.
And in this case I'm gonna go for the rectangular array
and specify ahead the number of the shapes
that I want in the X direction.
So in the, um,
in the red axis, like for example six,
then the number, uh, for the columns, let's say again six.
And the number in the Z in this case we're working flat,
so it's going to be just equal to one.
And then
we can space them, uh, once again with the math
or with our mouse
And confirming the selection when we are done 40.
And basically that's it.
This is, uh, what we want to achieve.
Just before, um, laser cutting the old models
in rhino, you can just, uh, um,
you can actually specify the color as well.
Um, you might have this in different locations of,
of your interface.
Uh, here on the Mac, on the Rhino seven, you find, um,
let's say printing settings, width of the line
and the properties under, um, here the gear
in the properties panel.
Sometimes you also, uh, find, uh, the properties here.
So for example, the lines has to be continuous.
Uh, if it's easier, you can already specify the color
or the layer that has to match the color of your lines.
So let's say to LGB color.
And so once again, 2 55, 0, 0 for red.
So you can select everything, make a group,
make other copies, rotate if it's easier,
move them, export them.
And again, um, produce the nesting file in another software.
Uh, this is the history.
Basically all the commands that I uh, used
to create this kind of file.
And you should basically find, uh, be able
to find here the properties object
and then select uh, display color by layer
because we put it red line type has to be continuous.
And the print width, the most important one
for the laser cutter has to be headline.
Once this part is done, you can just go to file
and site to export or save.
You can also do export selected if you have multiple objects
and you only want to export, uh, this file for example.
And then you have many formats to choose from.
So it is a vector file.
We can use uh, daf,
we can use
SVGI
usually work uh, with pdf F.
Sometimes if you export an SVG or
or DWG, you might have double lines.
This is a problem that I have for Mac and with RiNo.
So we can try, um, we call it modules.
We can export, yes.
And if everything is fine, let's see,
we already have one file here.
We can make another port
and import.
We can go the other way around.
So open this one illustrator
and be sure to work in the original size.
Okay, I don't have double lines, I just have
profiles that are not joined.
So if this happens, you can just, you need
to clean up a little bit.
The file, you can select all of them.
Yeah. And then um, it um,
control j conman J
yeah in RiNo you can just be sure, uh,
to have them joined.
This icon is for exploding all of them.
And this one to join them in closed loops.
And just to be sure, you should um, be able
to see a popup appearing.
It's a bit hidden in the Mac is all the way down,
but the windows is um, is on top.
Then we can try example to the file.
Um, export.
Yeah, we can try PDF is better. Um, the stream,
You already have a preview.
We can open any skip this time
every time.
Be sure that you're working on the size one-to-one.
If it's a PDF, you want to embed it as well.
And then you have all the list of the paths,
so all the vectors of the lines
and you're able to create any other
notification that you want.
So you can enlarge them, you can
change the color,
you can create perforations, you can add other modules,
parts that will be cut out at the end.
And once again, when you export, be sure
that you select everything and you specify the stroke paint.
Red is good, green is good, blue is good.
2 55, 0, 0. And the stroke line to be her line.
And uh, and yeah, and that's it.
Then you can just keep on exporting this as a vector file.
So P-D-F-S-V-G, DAF or any of those.
So if you print them all out on the leather
cutter, this is the result.
And if you print them with two colors,
you can really also play
and try out different configurations.
You can put the fingers so where you can see better.
So this should be the result.
I take literally, um, couple of minutes to, to laser cut
all this, file, all these modules.
And then you just have to do this way.
So you can fold this kind of arrows
that we just created a little bit or using the tweezers
and you just try to open a little bit this uh,
female slot, then pull
it the way.
Uh, for example, I'm using felt.
So it's something very so easy to, for prototyping,
I'm very versatile
and if you do this kind of test,
you should be able to get a stable connection.
This also depends on the material that you're using
and on the thickness, if you have for example,
another line here, like a double line, this will allow you
to block much better this kind of joint.
And you have many possibilities.
So you can also work on the back
or you can also uh, assemble them in another way
so they become more 3D.
Any shape will be allowing you to create bags
and three structures.
It's just the way, the way you assemble the models together.
And you can use them for different applications.
So this can be an accessory, this can be a glove,
this can be a holder, this can be a bag.
And of course you can mix
and match, especially if you have a design,
similar connections.
So same lines, different shapes.
So you can add this
and remove the blurring.
So you can have something like this.
As I was saying, you can have double
connection like in this case.
So we have another module, another shape
that has double female joints.
And you can have this kind of um, male part
that is completely different that allows you, for example,
to join a different pieces in the back.
So you can have also
Something made like that.
Yes, this one is actually wool felt. It's a bit softer.
And this one is very thin. Synthetic felt.
The synthetic felt uh, works a bit better
because it's a bit stiff
and the laser cutter actually seals the edges.
So there is nothing a trace or tears.
It's very easy to work, uh, with this kind of material.
It's not the best one,
but it's very easy to prototype a couple of connections.
Yeah, yeah, of course. So you can do fewer.
I just made four because I think it's easier
and you have just four possibility for interlocking them
and create something that expands in different directions.
At the same time,
you can also have eight different connections.
You just have more possibilities.
So for example, you can copy the four
and nest all of them inside so you have more layering
and your connection will be more stable like,
uh, also in this case.
And of course you can play with the size so they don't have
to be the same size.
Like the lines can be smaller, can be longer,
or you can keep on iterating the models that we just made.
And for example, I showed yesterday's example,
you can also redesign the kind of connection
that you want to appear in between.
So this is as is kind of a flower
instead of being a simple triangle
or I have another one here to share.
So you can also have something like this.
This is a very simple one, it's just one polygon.
So now everyone is able to do something like that.
So this is just gon
with different slots,
like one per edge.
And then there is this little parts that act like maze
that lock in place.
The two shapes, they have like a kind of T-bones.
So there are completely two different modules per
size also.
And this allows you to create this kind of, uh, structure
that can be used 3D for a lamp
or can become
completely 2D like a mat or a carpet
or can become a hat, a bag or whatever you want.
Yeah, synthetic felt is not totally okay.
This is, um, pretty less than one millimeter.
So it, the laser stays on the modules very little time.
It's pretty fast.
So it can be done, the wool felt is better,
just the smell won't be good.
And of course you can have perforations for example,
if you want to add additional materials, you can add dreads.
You can have engravings as a way.
Um, so to decorate your modules,
Uh, yeah, you can also make everything in Illustrator.
It's a matter of workflow.
If you want to keep using this uh, module,
for example in the 3D printing, then you can just uh,
say the design into future or in our in um, in rhino
and then keep going and right extrude
and you have your shape just in that case.
You may need to make these lines a bit wider
because you're gonna deal with that bit thicker material.
So in this case, we're not considering the thickness,
that's why we're just work with lines
because we're assuming that the material is very light,
like not thick at all.
If you're working with a material
that is more than one millimeter in thickness, then you need
to enlarge in engineering also a little bit
the females lots as well.
So keep this in mind.
Do you have any questions on uh, the software on Fusion,
on Rhino or on the 2D Vector software?
Also? For example, you can assemble the modules like this
so you can get some more like uh, three dps.
Yeah, you should run a couple of tests to specify, uh,
to understand what's the thickness of the lines
more or less, yes, it should match the thickness,
but it depends the kind of material that you have
because some materials, you know, like the cotton,
so it depends how much this part will
open, not just the thickness.
It's a good practice to work with. Um, little connection.
Even this one for example, is just one millimeter,
but this line is pretty big
and if I don't have something
that matches this part, this will be loose.
The moment I connect with another male part,
it can work.
So give it a try to both of the software
if you're still undecided,
I use, um, all of them.
I'm still not very comfortable with blender,
but I also really believe that um, this kind
of workflow can happen there.
There's a lot of people that also use glass software.
Anyway, I will be staying with you this file.
So in case you want to go back to them
or keep on editing, uh, any
of these files, you can do that.
Try not to create models that are very small.
Sometimes it's very hard to assemble them together,
like in this case's kind of little
T-bones joints
or you're going to need a lot
of tweezers and a lot of time.
So usually I stay with this size like four centimeters,
five centimeters, or you can play uh, with a multiple of it.
So you can also have variations
if you're using a big thickness instead
of a line you can already create since the
beginning, a rectangle here.
And then pattern it for
how many times you want or you need.
If it's useful, I can also share that part.
So we are here
and for example, before making this, um,
well at any point we can actually
break our links and make it again.
So we have a line.
There are many ways again to do that
or we can just add our circle, our shape,
whatever it is, anxi, that obviously helps.
And then create a rectangle for example, um, here
that I can just add dimensions.
So let's keep our 10 millimeters, one centimeter
and then the width, like my thickness for example,
one millimeters is something, uh, that is going
to be very thick to be inserted inside or uh, 0.8,
escape the selection.
You can just select the part the we want to pattern
and then make a circular pattern.
So be sure for example here, no need to select the icons,
just select four the edges of your shape.
You can uh, clear the selection at any point.
1, 2, 3, 4, and then a center point.
And then for example, you want three or you want five.
So Five you
would just add more, um, ways to assemble your piece.
If you don't like five,
you can definitely put less than four.
So three and your design will change automatically.
And now you're able to see also the shape, uh,
a bit more clear because we don't have lines, we have slots.
So this in case you need the bigger thickness,
you can do finished sketch
or you can also example extrude it
for 3D printing next time.
And for example, um,
0.5 millimeters.
And this is one of the shape that you can create, um,
in 3D.
That means that you have a body now and of course a sketch
and you can also export the body as a mesh, so as STL.
But this is something that will be, uh,
probably needed in a couple of weeks or more.
So this is just uh, uh, for the sake of the demonstration.
'cause if you work uh, with a platform like Fusion 360
or Rhino, you just have many possibility
to have the software and keep it in use
for other assignment or other projects.
Yeah,
Yeah.
Maybe last thing that I can show about, um,
lemme share the screen,
but fusion that I forgot to mention is
that you have the possibility to write, uh,
values also in here when you have um,
the dimension values
or you can write the mathematical expressions.
So for example, you want this to be, um, as big
as the distance of this lot.
So you can just click here for example.
Now it'll be applied to all the patterns.
So some there're so big that will call collide
or you can write, uh, it's going to be 10
divided by two minus 10.
So you can also write your own function here.
Sometimes it doesn't make sense
or the other way around you can have this value
plus hundred.
So you don't have two to calculate.
You can let the software to the operation for you,
or in this case again, doesn't have any sense.
But if there are more parameters
that you can take into account since the beginning,
it's also good to add a function here.
And you have kind of a simulation.
Everything, uh, that you want to adjust needs
to happen in the, in the sketch
we design in the sketch, the rest are just, uh, operations
that can be 3D or animations.
But the location to specify, uh, dimensions
and relationships happens here.
And again, you can do a lot of things.
You can also do copy paste,
Do it manually if you prefer.
It is not recommended because you have a lot
of possibility in the software to automate things
and you can go back at any
point to what you did.
And for example, if you have since at the beginning a couple
of tick that you want to try, there is also the possibility,
uh, to create your own value.
So this thing is something you find under modify
and you can add your own parameters here.
So you have a menu that you can just create a parameter
where you can have a name like, uh, leather thickness,
you can write 1.2
and then instead of 0.8, you can just click um,
select letter thickness.
This also, yeah, or the other way around.
You can write letter thickness here, confirm.
And then under modify change the value here
through 0.5 and you see that this got updated
or any other value,
but in case it's useful it can
also work, uh, like that.
And I don't know if there is, uh, more questions.
I hope all of you somehow managed
to create a module or a couple of those.
I hope you will do something more creative than
what I showed you because this is just a starting point
and you have many references uh,
out there you can see on os circular fashion.
So many inspirations,
many great projects developed in public academy.
If you have them try to disassemble to understand
how the things things are made, how the connection can work,
but also can be improved.
And I will be sharing this by in math most,
and I think if nobody has questions, we can just,
um, close the session.
Yeah. Okay. And thank you so much.
Uh, I hope it was clear enough
to understand at least the fundamentals of the software.
And uh, please let me know if you need any help.
You can post in the Matmos channel.
I can put a screenshot so I can, uh, I also have an idea,
uh, where is the problem?
What is the problem? And, uh, have fun.
Thank you. Bye. Thank you. Bye-bye. Thank you. Thank you.
Thank you. Thank you Byebye.
Your collections, document everything. Bye everyone.
See you in the next, uh, week's record, um, review.
Bye.